guys welcome to concept and coding and
this is Shan and today we are going to
do o 2.0 okay so let's start it without
wasting any time or stands for open
authorization so it's an authorization
framework it enables secure third party
access to user protected data now let's
understand this two points with this
flow so this is
user let's say this user is already
signed into his Gmail
account this is his Gmail account
and user is already logged in right user
is already logged
in so this is it has its protected data
so this user it has its complete profile
right it's set up all there into the
Gmail
account now it want to log to any
other website let's say that certain XY
Z
website it want to log in
here it want to log in here so you might
be seeing that there we do get an option
that
right sign in
using Gmail right you get different
options so now let's say if user use
this sign in using Gmail what it is
trying to do is it is authorizing this
third party so XYZ website is a third
party right and it is authorizing this
third party hey you go ahead use my
protected data from the Gmail I am
authenticating you right so Gmail will
provide the information which is
required to this third party and after
that you would be able to log to this
XYZ website and you will see that you
will see that hey welcome user so it
automatically get your username and
everything from the Gmail so there are
four important roles or you can say that
actors involved in it this process in
this process four actors
involved first one is resource owner who
is this resource owner in this
flow this guy is the resource owner so
now let's say
that I am the
person who has this Gmail account Shan
I am already signed in over here and
this guy is me shran so who is the
resource
owner here this this me Shan is the
owner then second one is client who is
the client the client is one which
initiate the request so in this case
let's say I want to uh I want to access
Facebook and here I am clicking
that sign in using
Gmail so now in this case Gmail uh
Facebook is the one which wanted my
protected data right so who is the
client here
this third one is authorization server
so now let's say that Gmail so there
would be another you can say
that
Gmail authorization server so generally
sometimes you will see that even in the
Gmail itself one one service itself
taking two roles it is also doing
authorization uh part also and also the
resource like it holds the resources
right so but for simplification and in
most of the cases generally these are
two different components right so there
would be one Gmail authorization server
which takes care of authorizing right so
this is the third
component and the fourth is resource
hosting server so I am the resource
owner and where is my all the resource
present currently in the Gmail in Gmail
knows about me everything my date of
birth my name my email ID right all my
data is present into the Gmail right and
Gmail is hosting it so this is the
hosting server my resource are present
into the Gmail
and this is the server which is hosting
my protected data so here in this case
Gmail is your
resource hosting server so you got this
four resources you have to be very clear
because we are going to see the flow
using this only so now these are the
four actors involved in
it and we will see a flow using this
four actors now but before starting the
flow I will tell
you there
are five
mechanism to get the token or you can
say that to get to authorize a
client so one very very important and
popular is authorization code
Grant right this one I also cover this
but these are just normally not you can
say that encouraged but this is the
important part authorization code Grant
right and refresh token Grant is also
used but we will cover
all right so you you will get to know
that but it's a mechanism used by client
to obtain access token you will get to
know about access token and all so don't
worry about it and now let's see of flow
of authorization code Grant this one I
am telling you the flow off for
this so these are the four clients
resource owner
client Gmail authorization server and
Gmail resource server right the use case
is that I am the resource owner I want
to log to
Instagram and I am already logging to my
Gmail so Gmail has known about my uh
name age date of birth email ID address
so Gmail I have have all the data
Instagram wanted to use this to help me
to sign in and Gmail also has its
authorization
server so now what's the
flow so I telling you about
authorization code Grant now
first so now first Instagram has to do a
registration
with authorization server so it has to
do register so if Instagram has to show
an icon here
that sign
in US using Gmail sign in using Gmail so
first it has to register to this
authorization server and this Gmail
authorization server will return two
things client ID and client secret right
so now Gmail authorization server knows
about this Instagram right so this is
your client ID this is your client
secret which only authorization server
and only client should know this
secret okay okay so first client has
done its registration and got its client
ID and
secret now user want to login to an
insta so I am the resource owner let's
say I come to uh I am the resource owner
I want to log to
Instagram and I instead of putting my
username password I clicked on sign in
using Gmail I am already uh have a Gmail
account I have all the information there
and I chose this option that hey sign in
using Gmail
now what client will do client will
redirect me to authorization server
Gmail authorization server so it will
redirect me to the authorization
server where I have to authenticate
myself I if I am not logging to Gmail I
have to provide my username ID of the
Gmail and I have to authenticate right
and also provide the consent so you
might have seen that you uh Gmail would
might show you you are providing this
this this permission to Instagram are
you okay with it and you have to provide
yes provide it so you are providing
nothing but a
consent okay once you provide the
consent authorization server will goes
to the
insta and provid it the authorization
code one code will be given which is
known as authorization
code Now using this authorization code
insta again call the authorization
server and ask for the token hey give me
the token
now now what would happen is when you
ask for a token or Gmail authorization
server will provide you two things
access
token and refresh
token right so exess token is a short
live maybe let's say 10 minutes or 15
minutes right but if it is expired you
can use refresh token which is a
generally Long Live token right to get a
new access token I we will come that in
later but currently you have to
understand the
flow so what happen is when Instagram
asks for token using the authorization
code authorization server will provide
two token access token and refresh token
okay now using this access token
Instagram will goes to this Gmail
resource server where my data is hosted
name age address wherever
right and it say that hey this is the
exess token give me this data now what
it will do is this Gmail resource server
what it will do it will go call the
authorization server and he say hey
validate this token I got this token is
it valid or
not uh authorization server validate
this right and return whether it's a
valid or
invalid right if it is invalid it will
discard the request if it is is valid
then it will provide information
whatever it is asked let's say your
profile so your name age email ID would
be shared to Instagram and after that it
would sign in you
successful right if you're if your token
is not valid and you are not authorized
it might certain 4xx might be
401 uh
unauthorized right
so this is generally the flow for this
authorization code
Grant so now let's see the request and
response for each flow but please note
right please follow the official
documentation man like the exact API
names or more parameters this API names
which I have taken this is just for like
to help you better
clarify right
this might not be an exact API names
right so that is just I want to say that
follow a proper rfc's right rfcs are
generally you can say that official
documentation for o you will see
different versions for explaining
different different
parts but I'm explaining the apis and
response by taking some uh sample API
name right which makes sense in the
context
okay now now first registration
process so what is the first step
Instagram the client has to register
itself to the authorization server so it
has to do the
registration okay so this is the
register so this is the post API
register and what it say that this is
the client name let's say my my app name
so here it might be passing let's say
Instagram
Instagram and it will pass the redirect
uis so it uh three three Uris you can
give Max three uis you can give where
you want redirect to happen right so so
it's a generally the call back so if you
see many times this Gmail has to
redirect right at many places at many
places it has to redirect
so you can Define three redirect uis
during registration itself so what is
the the response in response you will
get two things client ID and client
secret okay so registration process
clear this client ID and client secret
client secret is very very confidential
information which is only known by
client and authorization server right it
is generally used to authenticate the
client let's say in this case Instagram
to authorization
server okay authoriz uh this is
done okay this is done now the second is
when
the owner let's say in this case I
clicked on sign in using Gmail on
Instagram what it will has to do is it
will has to redirect me to the
authorization server so how it
does it invoke this Instagram now going
to invoke this API
authorize okay and what all the
parameter it passed while this API first
send that response type which is code so
what this response type
means this field is specified that the
desired response type from the
authorization server I want you to send
me authorization code in the response
that's what it specifies or you can say
that tell the authorization server what
is the expectation of the client here
response type should be some code
authorization
code it will pass its client ID
the client ID got in the first
step it will pass the redirect URI where
the call back should have
happened but if you see that redirect
urri is
optional if it is not present then which
redirect URI should be used
authorization server will use any one of
the uis which are defined during at the
time of
registration okay okay so redirect URI
is
optional if
provided it should match with one of the
URI provided during registration in
registration you can provide three
Uris right and during this fetching the
authorization code
part if you redirect URI if you are
passing then it should be one of the
redirect URI which you have defined at
the time of registration
right if not provided one will be picked
from the list during the registration
which you have given
okay then there comes the scope so scope
is
like Instagram want to access what all
information from your Gmail so it is a
space kind of thing so let's say I want
email access your profile access or
certain address access so there might be
different different Scopes right so
these are space separated and you can
tell like hey I want the scope for all
this data right so whatever the data
which you wanted to access this client
your client it will add it here in the
scope and the last comes the state so
state is some random value like sj1 some
random value it helps in protecting csrf
uh attack I'll tell you how but first
understand this API
right
so Instagram has
now redirect owner to the authorization
server right it has called this
API authorized and pass this
data now what response it will get right
so use user will do the authentication
there in the Gmail site if it is not
login it might have to provide username
password log to the Gmail and then Gmail
will show you a consent hey Shan like
Instagram want to access
your email profile and address are you
providing the consent for it if I click
yes then what it will do
is it will redirect now from the Gmail
authoriz
server it will take me to the redirect
API which I have provided here if I
haven't provided there it would be pick
pick from the one which has been defined
in the at the time of
registration and in the it will pass me
some authorization code here and the
state right so
now at this time when I am authenticated
and provide the
consent authorization server calls the
redirect URI the call back URI and pass
the authorization code right now
Instagram got the authorization
code now but you can ask me right hey sh
authorization code got it I understood
what is the purpose of this state in the
request in the request I am setting this
state let's say some random value
sj1 and in the
response authorization server also
returning me the same as J1 what is the
purpose so see state is recommended it's
not mandatory but it's recommended it
prevents csrf attack so now let's
understand this I'll tell you this
attack right so what happen is let's say
there is an
attacker and this is me owner Shan I am
trying to add let let's say
Instagram right and this is the attacker
and it has uh
Gmail authorization
server okay so now let's say attacker
has call at the
rate authorized API and in return it got
the authorization code it has got the
authorization code right
this
part whatever the authorization code
here now this authorization code
attacker has saved it it didn't use it
you can use authorization code only once
and attacker didn't use it now let's say
that I am the legitimate owner and this
is the legitimate
client I am trying to log to this using
Gmail right so in the Gmail
authorization server I have called
the authorized request this
request I have sent
this now I am waiting for this response
where I will get my authorization code
right but let's say that if this
attacker put its authorization code and
there a hey this is the
response right if it send its respon
code to me now Instagram might say that
hey okay I have I'm already waiting I
have already hit the authorize and I'm
waiting for Gmail authorization server
to send me the authorization code but
what happened is in mid attacker
intercepted the request and it send you
its own authorization code now Instagram
will say that yes I got the
authorization code Now using this
authorization code what it will do
is it
will request for
token
and Gmail will provides the
token okay now you got the authorization
code for the attacker now Instagram will
pass this authorization code attacker
authorization code and ask for token hey
provide me token now Gmail will provide
you
the token but this token is generated
from what attacker authorization code
not the Instagram which it
wanted now ultimately using this token
it will get it will call the Gmail now
and hey give me the details of this
token which I get now to whom details it
will send mine or
attacker it will send the attacker one
it will send the attacker one because
this authorization code is related to
the attacker so ultimately what I do is
I will get sign in to Instagram using
attacker just see about an app where you
login using Gmail of an attacker and
there you upload certain files where it
will upload to let's say you want to
upload certain to drive Google Drive
where it will get upload to it will get
uploaded to attacker one attacker Google
drive right so this is the csrf uh
attack cross-side request
forgery right so this is how uh State
comes into the picture where it
protect the legitimate client how so now
here if you see that
attacker and this is the Gmail attacker
call
the authorized
API and it will get its uh
code authorization code now attacker
saves it
now I am the
one which is trying to log to
Instagram so Shan wanted to log to
Instagram using Gmail so it Instagram
made request to authorization
server call this authorize API authorize
I have
set this state some random unique value
which is very difficult to guess right
so I have set also the state let's say
State I have said
SJ 111 right let's say some unique value
which is very difficult to understand
difficult to generate or guess now let's
say attacker
somehow pass me its response hey this is
the response your authorization code
right so attacker tried to send me its
authorization code right and in the
state it might be passing some random
number in the state but now what I will
do is that I will compare H the response
which I am getting the authorization
code and its state so I will compare the
state the one which I send
sj1 and the authorization code which I'm
getting also it has a so is it equal if
estate is not present I will discard
this
request if estate is present but it is
not matching with what I have
sent then also I have discard this
because it is not might be it's a csrf
attack because this response is not for
the one which I have sent the one
authorized request which I have sent I
have set the state
sj1 and when the Gmail authorization
server returns me the authorization code
it will also pass this state same sj1
then I will compare hey I got the
authorization code this state matches
with what I sent if it matches I will
accept this authorization
code so you got it what is the purpose
of the state Now using this
authorization
code what client will do is it will try
to fet the Token so now there is another
post token
API so it will put a grand type as
authorization code because we are doing
the first one right authorization code
Grant so the grand type is authorization
code what is the code you got so
authorization code then the first step
we got in the response right which
server said authorization code so we
pass it that the redirect URI it's an
optional if you don't pass the redirect
URI the one will be choose from the
registration uh at the time of
registration which you have
defined the client ID and client secret
so now here if you see that in this step
the client secret is used the client has
to authenticate itself that I am
authenticated one and this secret is the
confidential which clients get during
the
registration okay because using this
token you can access protected data so
client is also need to authenticate
itself so Grand type the grand code
which you get in the previous step the
client ID client
secret right and in the response what
you get is you got access token through
which you can access the protected
data it is a short live token expires in
3600 this is in seconds generally so
it's like 33 seconds is 1 hour right so
it will expire in 1 hour you can change
it this is just an example right so
generally it's a short live like expires
in let's say 15 minutes 30 minutes or
whatever and token type is beer what
does beer means as it tells the client
that you should pass this token in the
authorization header whenever you want
to access the protected
data and one thing you will get is
refresh token refresh token means so if
your access token expires you can
generate a new token using this refresh
token right I'll show you the refresh
token part also now this token value
right access token which you get either
it can be a JWT token or a plane string
itself right so JWT I will explain maybe
in the next hld topic what are the
format of JWT what all information it
can have but this token you can either
be play a string or JWT token
itself okay now you got now the client
Instagram got the excess token now what
it will do now it will call the Gmail
whatever the end point and get your
data right whatever the in the scope it
has uh got the token or code for so now
for all that scope email address
whatever the scope would be it can f the
data and using that it will help you to
sign
in but now let's say that your token got
expired so what you have you have to
renew it so how you will renew it use
using refresh token
and this refresh token is your another
grand type right so this authorization
Grand type is nothing it's a mechanism
to obtain the access token so using
Grand type refresh Grand type you can
get the access token so this is how it
is so I am calling the token again Grand
type is now refresh
token right and I will pass the refresh
token value here in this refresh token
whichever I got right redirect Ur
optional if you don't provide it one
will be used from the registration time
which you have provided the client ID
and the client secret so this is the
response you will get a new access
token right and the new refresh
token all right so if this expires you
can generate a new token using this new
refresh
token
likewise so this complete flow is clear
this complete flow API request and
response is clear this is for
authorization code Grant this is very
important so now there is another Grant
type is called implicit Grant this is
generally not recommended to use
generally authorization code Grant is
the one which is highly used but still
it better to uh discuss about this so
here in the authorization code grand
type what used to
happen Instagram and Gmail authorization
server it will ask for first authorized
hey give me and it will get code and
then using this code it will get the
token so in the implicit there is no
there is no two process you get the
token in the one process itself so in
the
authorized the response type is
token earlier in the authorization code
Grant what is the response type code hey
I wanted the expectation of the client
is from the authorization server that I
want code here authorization code in
this expectation is token the response
type it is expecting is token you have
to provide the client ID right whatever
the client
ID you have to provide the redirect Uris
optional
scope and
state right so here in the response you
will directly get access token
value right in the whatever the redirect
URI you will provide it right
here here in this URI itself you will
get the access token
information there is no refresh token in
implicit Grant why because there is
nothing like a uh like there is no two
steps here it's just like an authorized
during the authorized itself you can ask
a new
token then there is something called
resource owner password credential
Grant right resource owner password
credential Grant now in this here if you
see in the token API in the token API
what happen
is Grand type I will choose password
right this is the grand type so there is
no authorized API so here in this case
there is no authorization code no
authorization
call so here I am providing the resource
owner Shan I am providing my Gmail
username my Gmail
password client is passing Instagram is
passing its client ID secret the grand
type it has chosen is the password like
this is the grand type for this one and
the scope which it wanted to access so
in the authorization code grand type
here we are passing the
code
right right and for how to get that code
using authorized but here I don't need
code actually I am passing my username
password itself so that's why there is
no need for authorized API itself it is
directly calling this token API right so
I think this token API is post right we
can double check so I'm directly calling
this token API and passing my username
password itself right client ID secret
and all the scope which I wanted to
access and in the response it will
return me the access token refresh token
also right and using if this get expires
using refresh token I can renew it and
during renew using refresh token you
don't need to pass the username password
so Grant type is let's say refresh
token right you can pass client ID
client secret and also the refresh token
you can pass this one so you don't need
to provide username password at the time
of refresh token usage of refresh token
to get a new
access
okay and the last one is credential
client credential card so in this case
generally what this scenario is like
when resource
owner itself is the client so generally
earlier it was a scenario like this
right Shan Instagram and then Gmail so
here resource owner is different client
is different but in this client
credential
Grant client is also this resource owner
is also this so whatever the data it is
trying to access from let's say Gmail
whatever authorization
server the client is itself is the
resource owner in that case client
credential Grant is used right so it is
calling the token it's passing his
client ID client secret and the grand
type it says that client
credentials right and the
scope and the response it will get is
access token again there is no refresh
token required in this because it's just
like if you want if this got expired you
want to generate a new call the token
pass your client ID secret you will get
new right it's easy you don't have to
pass any username password or any code
with the same request you can get
generate a new token so there is no need
for uh authorization call
itself and also there is no refresh
token
also okay guys thank you and I if for
any questions ping me we can discuss
more thank you bye